A Guide to the Virginia Secretary of Transportation, Correspondence, 1979-1982
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Virginia Secretary of Transportation, Correspondence, 1979-1982
The Library of Virginia
32013
6 cu. ft. (6 boxes)
Virginia. Office of the Secretary of Transportation
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 32013 was transferred by the Office of the Secretary of Transportation, 633 9th St. Office Building, Richmond, Va, on 6 March 1984.
Biographical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties. Compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governors top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now.
Governor Linwood Holton's top priority for the 1972 session of the General Assembly was a proposal for a Governor's Cabinet, reorganizing state agencies into six major departments--each headed by a secretary appointed by the governor. Transportation and public safety was one of these six departments. The office of Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was created on April 8, 1972, by an act passed by the General Assembly. Governor Holton appointed Wayne A. Whitham, a member of the Winchester City Council, as the first Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety. When Whitham took office on July 1, 1972, he was responsible for State Highway Commission, Division of Motor Vehicles, Department of State Police, Highway Safety Division, Office of Emergency Services, Department of Military Affairs, Virginia State Crime Commission and the Law Enforcement Officers Training Standards Commission. The Office has undergone a series of administrative reorganizations since. On April 12, 1976, the Legislature established separate secretariats for transportation and for public safety, effective July 1, 1976. On July 1, 1984, the offices were again combined. Most recently, the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was divided into separate secretariats on February 22, 1990. The Secretary of Transportation is a member of the Governor's Cabinet, and is appointed by the governor, subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. The Secretary is responsible to the governor for the Department of Transportation, Department of Rail and Public Transportation, Department of Aviation, Department of Motor Vehicles, Virginia Port Authority and the Motor Vehicle Dealers Board.
Wayne A. Whitham, the first Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety, was reappointed by Governor-elect Miles E. Godwin, Jr., in December 1973 and by Governor-elect John N. Dalton in December 1977. Whitham suffered a heart attack in August 1978 and resigned in December 1978. On June 7, 1984, Whitham died in Richmond, Virginia. Governor Dalton named George M. Walters, a former top executive of the Reynolds Metals Corporation, to succeed Whitham as Secretary of Transportation. Walters served until the end of Dalton's term in January 1982. Governor-elect Charles S. Robb, the first Democrat to be elected governor since 1965, did not retain any of Dalton's cabinet secretaries. Robb appointed Andrew B. Fogarty, Dalton's assistant secretary for financial policy, as Secretary of Transportation. On July 1, 1984, the secretariats of transportation and public safety were combined again. As a result this partial reorganization of state government, Governor Robb appointed Fogarty Secretary of Administration and Franklin E. White, Secretary of Public Safety, assumed Fogarty's Transportation duties. White, who served as a White House liaison official under President Jimmy Carter, resigned in June 1985 to become the New York state commissioner of transportation. He was replaced by Andrew Fogarty who served until the end of the Robb administration. He later served as Governor Gerald L. Baliles chief of staff from August 1986 to October 1989 when he resigned to become a vice president with CSX Corporation.
In December 1985, Governor-elect Gerald L. Baliles, picked Vivian E. Watts, a northern Virginia legislator, as Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety. Watts served until the end of Baliles' term in 1990. In 1995 she was elected to her old seat in the Virginia House of Delegates. On February 22, 1990, the Secretary of Transportation and Public Safety was divided into separate secretariats. Governor L. Douglas Wilder, appointed John G. Milliken, a member of the Arlington County Board of Supervisors, as the Secretary of Transportation. Milliken resigned on December 17, 1993.
In February 1994 Governor George Allen, the first Republican elected governor since 1977, appointed Robert Martinez as Secretary of Transportation. Martinez was born in Cuba and had served as Deputy Administrator for the Marine Administration and Associate Deputy Secretary of Transportation during President George H.W. Bush's administration. At the end of Governor Allen's term in January 1998, Martinez joined the Norfolk Southern Corporation. Shirley Ybarra, deputy Secretary of Transportation in the Allen administration, was named Martinez's successor by Governor-elect James Gilmore. Ybarra previously worked as a special assistant to Transportation Secretary Elizabeth Dole during President Ronald Reagan's administration. Ybarra served until the end of Gilmore's administration in January 2002. Whittington W. Clement, a former lawyer and long-time member of the Virginia House of Delegates representing the City of Danville, was appointed Secretary of Transportation by Governor Mark R. Warner in 2002. Pierce R. Homer, Deputy Secretary of Transportation, replaced Clement in 2005.
Scope and Content
Contains files pertaining to Virginia transportation concerns in the form of Correspondence and Subject files, as well as, Budget files.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files
Series II. Budget
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence and Subject Files, 1979-1982., Extent: 6 boxes (5 cu. ft). (Box 1-5)
  The original order has been maintaned in the arrangement of this collection.
  - Aviation, Department of, 1979. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aircraft: Charges for State Planes, 1972-1980. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Aircraft: Governor Purchase Proposal, 1979-1982. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Aviation Licensing, 1979-1982. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Aviation, Organization and Management Study, 1979-1982. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Aviation Commission, 1979-1982. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Aviation Commission: Meeting Agenda and Minutes, 1979-1982. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Central Garage Car Pool Committee, 1979-1982. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Central Garage Car Pool Committee: Fleet Manager, 1979-1982. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Central Virginia Planning District Commission: Lynchburg, 1979-1982. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Coal Energy: Coal Haul Roads, 1979-1982. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Coal Exporting: Hampton Roads, 1979-1982. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Commission of State Governmental Management Report, 1979. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Commission of State Governmental Management, 1979-1982. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Emergency and Energy Services, Office of, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Emergency and Energy Services, Office of: Disaster Relief Act, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Emergency and Energy Services, Office of: Disasters, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Emergency and Energy Services, Office of: Disasters General File, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Emergency and Energy Services, Office of: Emergency Services and Disaster Law of 1973, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Emergency and Energy Services, Office of: Energy Division - Emergency Management of Resources Plan, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Emergency and Energy Services, Office of: Energy Division - Conservation Program, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Emergency and Energy Services, Office of: Energy Division - Miscellaneous, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Emergency and Energy Services, Office of: Office Space, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Emergency and Energy Services, Office of: Opperations Plans, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Emergency and Energy Services, Office of: Personnel Service Awards, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Emergency and Energy Services, Office of: Radiological Emergencies, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Energy: State Office of Emergency and Energy, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Hazardous Materials, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Highways and Transportation, Department of, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Highways and Transportation, Department of: Adjustable Work Schedule Study, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Highways and Transportation, Department of: Complaint, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Highways and Transportation, Department of: Escrow Procedures, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Highways and Transportation, Department of: Five Year Program, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Highways and Transportation, Department of: Highway Financing, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Highways and Transportation, Department of: Oil Re-Refinement Program, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Highways and Transportation, Department of: Public Transportation, 1979-1982. (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Highways and Insterstates: I-66, 1977-1978. (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Hopkins Commission, 1979-1982. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Hopkins Commission Reports, 1979-1982. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Joint Legislation Audit and Review Commission, 1979-1982. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Legislators: Virginia General Assembly, 1979-1982. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Legislature: New Members, 1979-1982. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - METRO Legislation: Washington Metropolitan Area, 1979-1982. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Metroploitan Planning Organization: Kingsport and Tennessee, 1979-1982. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Metrorail: Dalton News Conference, 1979-1982. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Metrorail: Dalton Statement for 101 mile Metro system, 1979-1982. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Metrorail: Funding, 1979-1982. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Metrorail: Governor Dalton's Statement on Capital and Operating Expenses, 1979-1982. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Metrorail: I-266, 1979-1982. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Metrorail: 10 Million Dollar Fund, 1979-1982. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Metrorail: Opening Ceremony, 1979-1982. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Military Affairs, 1979-1982. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - NVTC: Dalton Trip, 1977. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Metrorail: Dalton News Conference, 1979-1982. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Personnel: Compensation, 1979-1982. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Powhite Parkway, 1979-1982. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Rail: Accomack Northampton, 1979-1982. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Rail: Delmarva Advisory, 1979-1982. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Rail: Eastern Shore, 1979-1982. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Safety Transportation, Department of, 1979-1982. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Safety Transportation, Authority for Director, 1979-1982. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Transportation Safety Office Space, 1979-1982. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Transportation: Urban Mass Transit Administration - Section 5 Designation (Northern Virginia Transportation Commisssion), 1979-1982. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Transportation: Urban Mass Transit Administration - Section 5 Designation (Pennsylvania Transportation District Commission), 1979-1982. (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Transportation: Urban Mass Transit Administration - Section 5 Designation (Richmond Area), 1979-1982. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Transportation: Urban Mass Transit Administration - Section 5 Designation (Roanoke-Lynchburg), 1979-1982. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Transportation: Urban Mass Transit Administration - Section 5 Designation (Tidewater Transportation District Commission), 1979-1982. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Truckers: Strike, 1979. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Trucking: Deregulation and Other Truck Matters, 1979-1982. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Trucks: Weights and Sizes, 1979-1982. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Twin Trailers, 1979-1982. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Walters, George M. - Secretary of Transportation, 1979-1982. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Walters, George M. - Biography, 1979-1982. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Walters, George M. - Speeches, 1979-1982. (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Series II. Budget, 1980-1984., Extent: 1 box (1 cu. ft.) (Box 6)
  - 1980-1982 Budget VPA: Historical/Financial Reference Material, 1980-1982. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 1980-1982 Budget VPA, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Budget: Areas of Emphasis, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Budget: Recommendations to Governor, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Budget: Governor's Guidance Package, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Governor's Guidance Package, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Commonwealth Data Base, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Budget: general, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Budget Amendments, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Agency Targets and Guidance Memos, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Commonwealth Planning and Budgeting Systems, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Budget Preplanning Study Justification, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Revenue Projections, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Revenue Projections - Transportation, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Budget: Department of Aviation, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Budget: CAP, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Budget: Office of Emergency and Energy Services, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Budget: Virginia Department of Highways and Transportation, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Central Garage Car Pool - Financial Proposal, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Budget: Department of Military Affairs, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Budget: Department of Motor Vehicles, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Budget: Department of Transportation Safety, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Budget: Washington Metro Area Transit Commission, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Audits: Transportation Agencies, 1982-1984. (Box 6, Folder 24)